<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Articles of peace, friendship &amp; entercourse, concluded and agreed between England &amp; Svveden, in a treaty bearing date at Upsal the ninth day of May in the year of our Lord God 1654. Published by his Highness special commandment.</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Council of State.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1655</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 18 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A74591</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1065_4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R210504</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99869296</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99869296</idno>
            <idno type="VID">169261</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A74591)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 169261)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 159:E1065[4])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Articles of peace, friendship &amp; entercourse, concluded and agreed between England &amp; Svveden, in a treaty bearing date at Upsal the ninth day of May in the year of our Lord God 1654. Published by his Highness special commandment.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Council of State.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2] 163-168, 165-171, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Henry Hills and John Field, Printers to His Highness,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCLV. [1655]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: 2X-3A² .</note>
                  <note>Z1 missigned Z3.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Foreign relations --  Sweden --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sweden --  Foreign relations --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sweden --  History --  Christina, 1632-1654 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:169261:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ARTICLES OF PEACE, FRIENDSHIP &amp; ENTERCOURSE, Concluded and
Agreed between ENGLAND &amp; SWEDEN, In a Treaty bearing date at Upſal the
ninth day of <hi>May</hi> in the year of our LORD GOD 1654.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>blazon or coat of arms of the Anglo-Irish Commonwealth</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed by his Highneſs ſpecial
commandment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>Henry Hills</hi> and <hi>John
Field,</hi> Printers to His Highneſs, MDCLV.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="articles_of_peace">
            <pb facs="tcp:169261:2"/>
            <pb n="163" facs="tcp:169261:2"/>
            <head>ARTICLES OF Peace, Friendſhip and Entercourſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded
and agreed between <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Sweden.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">In a Treaty bearing date at Upſal, the ninth day
of May in the year of Our Lord God, 1654.</head>
            <div n="1" type="article">
               <head>I.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat from henceforth there be and remain a good, firm,
ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere and perpetual Peace, Ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Allyance and correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence between
the Protector and Commonwealth of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and
<hi>Ireland,</hi> and the Queen and Kingdome <pb n="164" facs="tcp:169261:3"/>of
<hi>Sweden,</hi> and all and ſingular their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, Kingdomes, Countries,
Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces, Iſlands, Plantations, Lands, Cities, Towns, People, Citizens, and
generally all their Subjects and Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants, ſo that each part treat and
uſe the other with all real friendſhip and affection.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="article">
               <head>II.</head>
               <p>The ſaid Confederates, their People, Subjects and
Inhabitants ſhall, as op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity is offered, take care of, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote the
welfare each of other. And ſhall advertiſe each other, upon knowledge
ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, of all imminent dangers, plots, and conſpiracies of Enemies
againſt the other; and, as much as in them lies, oppoſe, and hinder the
ſame. Neither ſhall the one Confederate, either by himſelf, or any
elſe, treat of, act, or attempt any thing to the prejudice and diſadvantage
of the other; his Lands or Dominions, in whatſoever place, whether at Sea or
Laud, Nor ſhall any way aſsiſt the Rebells or Enemies of the other, to
the damage of the Confederate, nor receive, or entertain within his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions,
any Rebel or Traytor, who ſhall attempt any thing againſt the others State,
much leſs afford them any Council, help or favour, or permit it to be done by
any of his Subjects, People and Inhabitants.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="article">
               <head>III.</head>
               <p>The ſaid Protector and Commonwealth, and the ſaid Queen
and Kingdome ſhall <pb n="165" facs="tcp:169261:3"/>take
diligent care, That, as much as in them lies, all impediments and obſtacles
be removed, which have hitherto interrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the freedome of Navigation and
Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce, as well between both Nations, as with other People and Countries
within the Dominions, Lands, Seas and Rivers of either. And ſhall ſincerely
endeavour to aſſert maintain, defend and promote the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid Liberty
of Navigation and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce againſt all the Diſturbers thereof, by ſuch
waies and meanes, as either in this preſent Treaty, or hereafter ſhall be
agreed upon. Neither ſhall they ſuffer, that either by themſelves, their
Subjects and people, or through their default, any thing be done or committed
contrary hereunto.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="article">
               <head>IV.</head>
               <p>That either of the aforeſaid Confederates their people and
Subjects, may without any ſafe conduct, licence, general or ſpecial freely
and ſecurely go and enter by Land, or Sea, in and to the Kingdoms, Countries,
Provinces, Lands, Iſlands, Cities, Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lages, Townes, whether walled or
un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>walled, fortified, or otherwiſe, Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens and whatſoever Dominions of the
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:169261:4"/>other, and there ſtay
and from thence return or paſs through; and in the ſame places, upon juſt
prices to procure, and have provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Victuals, for their uſe and
ſuſtenance and to be uſed with all friendly Offices. And that either
Confederate, their people and ſubjects may trade and have commerce in all
places where commerce hath hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to been exerciſed, in what Goods and
Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandiſes they pleaſe, and may freely im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port and export the ſame,
paying the cuſtoms which are due, and conforming themſelves to the Laws and
Ordinances of the ſaid Commonwealth and Kingdome, whether the ſame
reſpect, Trade, or any other right; which preſuppoſed, the people,
ſubjects and inhabitants of both Confederates, ſhall have and enjoy in each
others Kingdomes. Countries, Lands and Dominions, as large and ample
privileges, Relaxations, Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and immunities, as any other Foreiner at
preſent doth, or hereafter ſhall enjoy there.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="article">
               <head>V.</head>
               <p>No Merchants, Captains, and Maſters of Ships, Mariners, nor
any other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, Ships, Goods, or Merchandize be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to either
Confederate ſhall upon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny publique, or private account, by virtue of any
Edict General or ſpecial, within a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the Lands, Havens, Sea-roads, Coaſts,
or Dominions of the other, for any publick ſervice, or expedition of War, or
any other cauſe, much leſs for any private uſe, be fei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, embargued,
arreſted, forced by violence <pb n="167" facs="tcp:169261:4"/>or
be any way moleſted or injured, provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded onely ſuch arreſts, as are
conformable to juſtice and equity be not hereby prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, ſo be it they
are made according to the ordinary courſe of Law, and not granted upon
private affection, or partiality, but are requiſite for the adminiſtration
of right and juſtice.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="article">
               <head>VI.</head>
               <p>In caſe any of the Ships of either Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federate, whether of
War, or Merchants, belonging to the Subjects and People of either, be by
occaſion of Tempeſts, purſuit of Pyrates and Enemies, or any other
ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent neceſsity conſtrained to put into each others Havens, Roads or
ſhores they ſhall be received there with all kindeneſs and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity, and
enjoy all friendly protection, and be permitted to refreſh themſelves and
procure, at a reaſonable price, all things needfull for their ſuſtenance,
reparation, or uſe. Neither ſhall they be hindred from go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of the
ſaid Ports or Roads, at their pleaſure, without paying any cuſtoms or
duties. Provided they do nothing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Laws, Ordinances and
Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes of the place, which the ſaid Ships ſhall enter into or abide
in.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="article">
               <head>VII.</head>
               <p>In like manner, if any Ship or Ships, whether publick or
private, belonging to ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Confederate, their People and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, ſhall
within any the Coaſts or Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions <pb n="168" facs="tcp:169261:5"/>of
the other, ſtick upon the ſands, or be forced to lighten their burden, or
be wrack'd, or ſuffer any dammage, all friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly help and relief, ſhall be
given them upon a competent reward. And what ever ſhall be remaining of the
goods thrown overboard or after Shipwrack, or any other damage ſuſtained,
ſhall be kept in ſafe cuſtody, and reſtored to the owner, or whom the
ſaid Owner ſhall appoint.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="article">
               <head>VIII.</head>
               <p>In caſe the people and ſubjects on either part, whether
they be Merchants, Fac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, or Servants, Maſters of Ships, Mariners, or
ſuch others, who travel and inhabit within the Dominions of the other, or
thoſe who act on their behalf before any Court of Iudicature, for recovery of
their Debts, or for other lawful occaſions, ſhall ſtand in need of the
Magiſtrates help, the ſame ſhall be readily, and according to the equity
of their Cauſe, in friendly manner granted them, and Iuſtice ſhal be
admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred to them without long and unneceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary Delayes. Neither
ſhall they be any way moleſted upon any pretence in the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch of
their Affairs, in their Iourneying, Bargaining, and Receiving the Price of
their Commodities, but that all Love and Friendſhip be extended towards them.
And it ſhall be free for them on both ſides, in their paſſage to and
again, in each others Coaſts, Ships, Havens, and Publique Places, to wear
about them Armes for <pb n="165" facs="tcp:169261:5"/>their
proper defence, ſo be it they give no iuſt ſuſpition to the Governour
or Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate of the place, of any deſign againſt the publique or
private peace. But he eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially who behaves and demeans himſelf ſoberly
and inoffenſively, ſhall be protected from all injury, violence and
moleſtation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="article">
               <head>IX.</head>
               <p>The ſaid Confederates, and all and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular their people
and Subjects, may buy and export out of all the Countreys, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions and
Kingdomes of the other, all kinde of Armour and Proviſion of War, and may
ſafely and freely put in with their Ships, and arrive at each others Ports,
Havens and Shores, and there ſtay, and thence depart, they carrying
themſelves peaceably, and conformably to the Lawes and Cuſtomes of the
reſpective places, and not diſturbing the freedome of commerce therein. In
like manner the Ships of War ſhall have free acceſs to the Ports of either,
there to ſtay, and come to anchor, but not in ſuch numbers as ſhall
occaſion manifeſt ſuſpition, without the leave and conſent of that
Confederate firſt obtained, to whom the Port belongs, unleſs compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
thereto by tempeſt, force, or danger of the Sea, in which caſe they ſhall
ſignifie to the Governor, or Chief Magiſtrate of the Place, the cauſe of
their Arrival, and ſhall continue there no longer then the ſaid Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor
or Chief Magiſtrate ſhall permit, Obſerving alwayes and every where, the
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:169261:6"/>Lawes aforeſaid, and
ſuch as ſhall here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after be agreed upon.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="article">
               <head>X.</head>
               <p>The Subjects and Inhabitants of the Queen and Kingdome of
<hi>Sweden,</hi> may ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and freely travel in <hi>England, Scotland</hi>
and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the Dominions thereof, and paſs through the ſame
by Sea or Land, to any other Nations freely to traffique and have commerce with
them in all ſorts of merchandize, and to import and export the ſame. And
the people of the ſaid Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth ſhall enjoy the ſame freedome in the
Kingdomes, Dominions and Territories, of the Queen and Kingdome of
<hi>Sweden.</hi> Provided, the Lawes, Ordinances, and particular rights of each
Nation, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Trade and Commerce be obſerved on both ſides.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="article">
               <head>XI.</head>
               <p>Although in the preceding Articles of this preſent Treaty,
it be forbid to either Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate to yield any aid or aſſiſtance to the
E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies of the other; yet it is not to be ſo underſtood, as if either
Confederate having no War with the Enemies of the other, might not ſail to,
or traffique with the ſaid Enemies, notwithſtanding that the other
Confederate be in actual war with them; But it is only provided, That till a
more particular agreement be made concerning this matter, no goods called goods
of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trabanda,</hi> a Catalogue and Specification of which ſhall be
made within four monethes <pb n="167" facs="tcp:169261:6"/>after
the date hereof, ſhall be carried to the Enemies of each other without peril
in caſe they be taken, of being adjudged lawfull prize without hope of
Reſtitution.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="article">
               <head>XII.</head>
               <p>But leſt ſuch Navigation and Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of the one
Confederate, his People and Subjects by Land or Sea, with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Nations,
during the War of the other Confederate, ſhould redound to the preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice of
the ſaid other Confederate. And leſt goods of enemies, ſhould paſs
concealed under the name of friends; for the remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val of all ſuſpition and
prevention of fraud herein, it is agreed, That all Ships, Waggons, Wares and
men, belonging to either Confederate, ſhall in their paſſage, have
Letters of ſafe conduct, commonly called Paſſe ports, and Certificates
ſigned by the Governour, or chief Magiſtrate of the Province or City, from
whence they come, Of which Letters and Certificates ſuch forms ſhall be
obſerved as ſhall be mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually concluded upon, within the ſpace of four
Moneths, next after the date hereof. And whereſoever any the Merchandize,
goods, veſſels, or men belonging to either, their people and Subjects,
ſhall be met with either in open Sea, or in any Channel, Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, Road, Land,
or any other place by the Ships of War, publique or private, or by any the
People, Subjects and Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of the others, or ſhall happen to be in one
place with them, they producing their Letters of ſafe Conduct and
Certificates <pb n="168" facs="tcp:169261:7"/>aforeſaid,
ſhall have nothing further exac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of them, no ſearch made, either of
Goods, Veſſels or Men, much leſſe ſhall they receive any dammage,
injury or mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtation; but ſhall be ſuffered to paſs on with freedome
to purſue their occaſions. And if any the people and Subjects of ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
ſhall do, or commit any thing contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the proper ſenſe of this
preſent Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, either Confederate ſhall take care that ſevere
puniſhment be inflicted on the Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors, and cauſe full and ſpeedy
ſatisfac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to be made to the parties wronged, for all Coſts and
Dammages.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="article">
               <head>XIII.</head>
               <p>In caſe it ſhall hereafter happen, that, during this Amity
and Confederation, any of the people or Subjects of either, ſhall act or
attempt any thing againſt the ſame or any part thereof, either by Land,
Sea, or other Waters, this Amity, Confedera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Allyance, ſhall not be
thereupon in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted or broken of, but ſhall remain and continue ſtill in
full force and virtue. Onely in ſuch caſe the particular perſons which
have offended, ſhall be puniſhed, and no others; And that Iuſtice ſhall
be done and ſatisfaction made to all perſons inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, within twelve
Moneths after Demand thereof. And in caſe the perſons ſo offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as
aforeſaid ſhall not appear and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit themſelves to Iuſtice, and
make ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction within the ſaid Term, the ſaid per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſhall be
declared enemies to both <pb n="169" facs="tcp:169261:7"/>States,
and their eſtates, goods and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects whatſoever, ſhall be confiſcated
and employed to a due and full ſatisfaction for the wrong by them done. And
their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſhall be lyable to further puniſhment when they ſhall
come within the power of either State, as the quality of their of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence ſhall
deſerve. And that ſpeedy reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution and ſatisfaction be made for the
loſſe and dammage which either part hath ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtained from the other,
during the War be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>England,</hi> and the <hi>United
Provinces.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="article">
               <head>XIV.</head>
               <p>This preſent Treaty and Confederati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhall in nothing
derogate from any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eminence, right or Dominion of either Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federate within
any his own Seas, Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nels or Waters, but that they have and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the
ſame, in as full and ample manner as they have hitherto had, or as of right
belongs to them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="article">
               <head>XV.</head>
               <p>It being the primary intent of this League and Amity, that
each Confederate their people and Subjects might enjoy ſuch freedome of
Navigation and Commerce, as is deſcribed in the foregoing Articles, within
the <hi>Baltick, Sound, Northern, Weſtern,</hi> and <hi>Britiſh Seas,
Mediterranean</hi> and <hi>Channel,</hi> and other the Seas in <hi>Europe;</hi>
Therefore all ſincere endeavour ſhall be uſed on both ſides by common
adviſe, aid and aſſiſtance, that the aforeſaid mutual Liberty of
Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vigation <pb n="170" facs="tcp:169261:8"/>and commerce,
be eſtabliſhed, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moted, and as occaſion is, defended againſt all the
Diſturbers thereof, who ſhall go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to interrupt, prohibit, hinder or
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain and limit the ſame to their own will and pleaſure, in prejudice
of the ſaid Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates. And either part ſhall with all Willingneſſe
or readyneſs, promote the good and prevent the hurt each of other; Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
the Treaties which either Nation hath made with other Kingdomes, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealths
and nations. And neither Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federate ſhall hereafter make any League or
Agreement in prejudice of this preſent, with any other People or Nation
without the privity and conſent of the other, or if any ſuch Agreement be
hereafter made, the ſame ſhall be reputed null and void, and give place to
this preſent Treaty. But as for the manner of giving aid and aſſiſtance
each to other for the defence of this League and of the Liberty of Commerce and
Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vigation, a more particular agreement, as need ſhall require, ſhall be
made thereupon accommodated to the circumſtances of time and other
affairs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="article">
               <head>XVI.</head>
               <p>For what concerns other Commodities, which Ships of War may
enjoy, and the Lawes by which they ſhall regulate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves when they
arrive in each others Ports and Harbours; and for what concerns com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce to be
exerciſed in <hi>America,</hi> as alſo the advantages of the
<hi>Herring,</hi> and other Fiſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, the execting Staples for Trade, and
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:169261:8"/>other Things and
Conditions which ſhall be found requiſite for the better clearing of the
foregoing Articles, Reſolution ſhall be had therein according to what
ſhall be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed upon in a diſtinct and peculiar Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty or Contract.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="article">
               <head>XVII.</head>
               <p>Whatever is agreed on in the foregoing Articles ſhall be in
force and vertue from this preſent time, and be truly obſerved on both
ſides by all ſuch as are within each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Allegiance. And for the
further Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation thereof, ſhall be ſubſcribed, ſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and
ratified by the Protector of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth of <hi>England, Scotland</hi>
and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the Dominions therto belonging, in the name of his
Highneſs and the ſaid Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, and by her Majeſty of
<hi>Sweden,</hi> under the handwriting and Seals of their ſaid Highneſs and
Majeſty, within four Moneths next enſuing the Date of theſe
Preſents.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
